<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Concept Basics on The Essence of Software</title>
    <link>https://essenceofsoftware.com/tutorials/concept-basics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Concept Basics on The Essence of Software</description>
    <image>
      <url>https://essenceofsoftware.com/eos-twitter-card.png</url>
      <link>https://essenceofsoftware.com/eos-twitter-card.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Daniel Jackson</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://essenceofsoftware.com/tutorials/concept-basics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Apps are state machines</title>
      <link>https://essenceofsoftware.com/tutorials/concept-basics/apps-are-state-machines/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://essenceofsoftware.com/tutorials/concept-basics/apps-are-state-machines/</guid>
      <description>If user experience runs deeper than the user interface, we need a way to talk about an app that isn’t just visual, and that captures behavior in a more fundamental way.
Programmers think in terms of complicated things like objects, callbacks, streams, functionals, and so on. They’re essential for structuring code, but for behavior a much simpler model is effective.
State machines That model is the state machine. You’ve probably come across state machines, either in a class about the theory of computation, or seeing diagrams like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operational Principle</title>
      <link>https://essenceofsoftware.com/tutorials/concept-basics/operational-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://essenceofsoftware.com/tutorials/concept-basics/operational-principle/</guid>
      <description>A compelling way to explain how something works is to tell a story. Not any story, but a kind of defining story that shows, through a typical scenario, why the thing is useful and fulfills its purpose.
The Minuteman Library Network, for example, offers a wonderful service. If I request a book, then when it becomes available at my local library, I get an email notifying me that it’s ready to be picked up.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
